everybody in from the lobby. So, we'll
go ahead and do that now.
And
so, it'll just take another moment or so
for folks in the lobby to join fully
into the meeting. But, uh, at this
point, the meeting the recording has
started. So, just as a reminder to
everybody uh that, uh, we do ask to keep
language to be appropriate for a public
meeting as we do post these uh, down the
road. on uh the program website and want
to ensure that anybody who is joining in
to listen uh actually is does not have
to be concerned if there are young ears
listening. Uh for just to introduce my
name is Dr. Dr. Dominic Zerlo and I am
the center director for the New Mexico
Department of Health Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin. And this is the
medical psilocybin advisory board
meeting on August 14th with Ian Dunn as
the chair. And so with that, I will turn
it back over to you, Ian. And uh and it
is your meeting.
>> Good afternoon, everyone. So glad to see
everyone's faces again. Uh my name is
Ian Dunn. I am the chair of the New
Mexico Medicals Psilocybin Advisory
Board. Uh I call this meeting to order
at 10:01 p.m. Um thank you Dominic for
the introduction. I will now allow the
board members to introduce themselves as
well if someone from the department
could call the role.
>> Absolutely. And I'll go ahead and do
that portion Ian. So uh first on the
list we have Brenda Burgard. Brenda,
>> hello everyone. Thank you. This is an
honor to be here today and um I'm I
chair the education and training for the
department of health and welcome
everyone here today. Thank you.
>> Thank you Brenda. And next is Chris
Piscus. Chris.
>> Hello everyone. My name is Chris Piski.
I'm a facilitator, licensed facilitator
in Colorado and I'm a veteran appointee
to the advisory board. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Chris. And next is Dan
Jennings.
>> Everybody, Dan Jennings. I'm uh vice
chair co-chair of the board and also the
chair of the research and continuous
improvement committee. Glad to be here.
Good to see everybody.
>> Thank you, Dan. And next is Dr. Larry
Leman.
Larry Leman, University of New Mexico.
Good to see everybody here. I'm chair of
the end of life committee.
>> Thank you, Dr. Leman. And next we have
Kenan Ryan.
>> Kenan Ryan. I'm the acting chief medical
officer for Medicaid, uh, serving as the
voting delegate from the Medicaid
director, Alana Kansas.
And that is all that I see in attendance
right now, Ian. So, I will turn it back
over to you.
>> Perfect.
>> I was just going to say, did you want me
to introduce uh the staff from the
department?
>> Yes, that's actually what I was about to
ask.
>> My apologies on that. Uh and since we
have a fair number of staff, I will just
go through and uh introduce individuals.
So we have Kathy Ajieri who is our
project manager with the center. We have
Carmen Batista who is one of our health
educators. Raymond Gyos who is an
analyst with the program. Uh Jorge
Gonzalez who is our program manager for
the medical psilocybin program. Brenda
Martinez who is our deputy director.
Johnny Musher who is our uh uh
management analyst and [clears throat]
also uh handles a lot of our scheduling
and logistics including for these
meetings. Rosalie Nava who is our um uh
Rosalie is our health program manager.
Leslie Peterson who is our compliance
officer, Cyrus Routman who is our
environmental scientist. Vicente Royal
who is our intern for this summer. And
then um I believe that's everybody. Uh
and my apologies. We also have Selena
Mononttoya who is our financial uh
manager and director. Um and now uh Ian,
we do have Desba has actually joined. So
Desba, if you would like to introduce
yourself as a committee member or as a
board member.
Uh I'm Desba. Nice to be here. Thank you
for all coming.
And with that, back to you, Ian.
>> All right, so today's agenda is pretty
simple. Uh, we just need to go over um
updates from the program, updates from
the committee, um, and then setting our
next priority in terms of what needs to
be accomplished next in the rules. Um,
but does the department have any uh
updates that they would like to provide
at this time?
>> Thank you, Ian. So, uh, what I would
like to do is just to update, um, one of
the things that we, we talked about this
a little bit actually this morning in
the end of life committee, uh, end of
life care committee meeting. And that is
that, um, we are almost ready to open up
the applications for cultivation and
producers. And so that should open up in
a over the next week to week and a half.
And once that is ready to open, we'll be
sending out notification through the
constant contact. and of course also uh
through our communications here at the
department. Um so we're looking forward
to that. We have already had several
inquiries with regard to it. Um at least
three that I'm aware of and several
others that uh of individuals or
organizations who are asking questions
with regard to it and so we look forward
to that and hope to have that process
completed pretty soon. Now, one thing to
note as a question that came up is there
are no fees for that application. If
individuals or organizations who are
interested on the production side have
questions about what will be needed,
they can actually go to the current
rules that have been promulgated and
they can see them there. Uh really what
we'll be doing with the when we say the
applications will open up is it will be
an online system and so really it will
just follow through the requirements as
they are outlined in the rule. But in
the meantime people are welcome to read
through that rule uh and they are
welcome to call or uh email us with
questions and the email is a little bit
further up there in the chat for
everybody in the meeting. It's the
medical.silicon
do.nm.gov. gov and we're looking forward
to that process. Um the other aspect
just to let everybody know with regard
to rules is we are continuing forward
with the additional rules um and we are
anticipating and releasing that next set
of rules with regard to the training and
education here at the end of this month
um and having that meeting towards the
end of September early October. Now, one
thing just to clarify, it seems there
are still uh quite a few people who
think once the rules are published for
that meeting that they are set in stone
and that they don't change. We do make
changes to them. We do continue to
receive public comment um and to make
adjustments and that includes through to
the rule hearing and even after that
based upon th that comment. The other
aspect is that really what we're looking
at doing is making sure that we have the
rules so that we can see and enough
rules so that we can see the first
patients in December. It does not mean
that we will uh that we stop at that
point. We actually continue as we've
said many times um just for this the
remainder of this calendar year that
really is to get the initial rules. We
will continue to have other aspects of
the program that will be added to or as
rules adjusted or changed and especially
if there are changes that are needed
based upon whether or not for example if
there's barrier that was unanticipated
or uh something that actually comes up
that you know nobody really anticipates
or some other changes we will be
continuing to have rule making process
through really I I would anticipate over
the next several years as the program is
implemented and as there is new research
available and so we do have that process
going on. Um, one thing we also did uh
we did announce this morning just
because we've had a few people ask about
the number of meetings and one of the
things I'd just like to say is and
especially as a thank you to this board,
the members of the board, the members of
the committees, all of the people who
have been participating is that so far
we have had over 70 meetings um with
regard to all of the different
committees and the boards. Um and uh
since most of those meetings range
between an hour and a half to two hours,
we estimate that that's anywhere between
about 120 to about 150 or 60 hours that
people have put in and that's just in
the meetings. So that doesn't include uh
times where for example in the research
committee they have um some other
subgroups that have been meeting to you
know do presentations and determine
things. So that's not including all of
that other those other aspects. Um and
uh but I just would like to once again
on behalf of the department thank
everybody for all of that work that's
been being done because it is really
helpful and uh as we do that and as Greg
Evans says in the uh in the chat 1
million hours sometimes it definitely
feels like it's approaching that and
reality is when I say that it's between
that 120 and that 150 or 160 that's just
sheer hours that doesn't actually mean
how many um you know in employment areas
we would say staffing hours because
think about how many people are on each
of these meetings. So if you have a
two-hour meeting and say there's 10
people on that meeting that's really 20
hours for all of those individuals who
are involved. So if we actually were to
expand that out we we are talking about
hundreds of hours that multiple people
many people have been committing to this
process. So just once again on behalf of
the department I'd just like to say
thank you because it is appreciated and
it is noted and it is a lot of work that
people have been engaging in. So thank
you very much and I think at that point
those are all the updates that I have
Ian but let me just double check with
Jorge. Jorge did you have anything I
miss?
>> I do not at the moment but I did put the
link to the adopted rules in the chat.
for the producer and laboratory. So if
you want uh you did mention those,
Dominic, so if folks want to take a look
at that, please do.
>> Thank you very much, Jorge.
>> Perfect. And then I do see Chris's hand
up.
>> I was just wondering if you could
clarify what date you're planning on
publishing the rules.
Uh the record and archives date is the
25th of August is when we plan on
publishing those
and again those are proposed rules. So
um but please when that happens we will
as usual send out a notice so people
will have access to them as well.
All righty. And then um if that's all we
have for that then I will go ahead if
you could call the role again um and
just give an update from the committees
from each of the chairs.
>> Absolutely. Uh so
let's see here. Uh pardon me everyone. I
have to switch screens. Okay. And I'll
just go ahead and go in order listed. Um
so Brenda Bhart you are first up.
>> Thank you. Um so our next meeting will
be for education and training will be on
the 21st from 9 to 11. Um I will be
meeting with the subeducation training
committee hopefully on Monday. I'm
trying to get everyone ready for that
and uh to go over uh where we are uh as
far as education and training goes. Um
it seems to me that um a lot of the
things that um are still were still
being discussed but I think we are um
coming to or have come to the consensus
of what practicum and um teaching will
be and so uh that's going to be um uh
top topic on our next meeting and um
probably talking about how uh this is
all going to roll out as far as um where
things are going to be taught. Um things
um education's going and training is
going to be taught and uh so uh we're
going to be uh reviewing a lot of those
topics. Um so far uh things seem to be
moving along the way they need to and uh
so that's all I've got right now.
Thank you, Brenda. And next is Chris
Pascus.
Uh I was the chair of the propagation
committee and those rules have been
published and already gone through the
rules hearing. So, I saw Jorge put them
the link to that
uh set of rules in the chat if anybody's
curious.
Um but I there's no updates from any we
haven't had a propagation committee in
months. So,
>> and thank you, Chris. And uh yeah, and
great work again on with those rules and
getting things moving forward. So, thank
you again.
Uh so next up we have Dan Jennings. Dan,
>> thank you. I appreciate it. Uh our
research and uh continuous improvement
committee has uh met every month and
August 7th was our last committee
meeting. Uh at that time the uh
committee had presented and approved uh
different
uh best practices for uh harm reduction
quality improvement framework including
four different tiers for routine
challenging experience adverse uh
experience and serious adverse
experience and two different reporting
frameworks uh that uh they've reached
consensus on. So our next committee
meeting will be September 11th at which
time we'll go over the core and extended
data set uh recommendations and so we
hope to see everybody there and
appreciate all the work that the
committee has put in the subcommittees
have put in on coming to that. We've
also had great dactic presentations from
the open network from Dr. Roman Pitzky
and from Nathan Oaks on data security
and data privacy. So, we try to always
have a a really good guest speaker. So,
that way in case uh you're wanting to
attend, we would love to see you there
for those. And of course, they're
recorded. So, if you wanted to catch up
on some of the back clicks, then hope
you get to see it on the YouTube side.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dan. And next up is Dezba.
>> Thank you. Um so, a couple updates. Uh,
next committee meeting is Tuesday, uh,
the 18th at 3:00 p.m. Mountain time,
3:00 to 5. Um, I am hoping that I'm in
confirming with Marina Robbins that
she'll be presenting um, some
information for that. Um I was able to
meet along with um Dominic and the staff
with the tribal liaison and some um
indigenous health workers um the other
last week as well. Um it was well
attended. Um so we were able to kind of
make some contact there. Um as well as
had a lively conversation in our last
meeting. um still trying to tackle the
$630,000
uh equity fund. Um there are a lot of
variables that we are still trying to um
figure out. Um so we need math math
geniuses to kind of come through um and
help kind of think about it. But part of
what was making it um a lively
discussion
um was just mainly you know
understanding as as far as like this the
main focal points of how that money is
going to be utilized. We want to get you
know as many people as possible um and
have the best outcome with the money
that's being used um primarily but again
it dep depends on the variables of the
cost of of the medicine itself sessions
and um also discussing how um that this
is you know how it will be used in
conjunction with Medicare and or other
types of um funding that will mitigate
the cost and the use of of this funding
and how it will be used. Um so please
definitely come to uh share your
information um or your expertise or your
thoughts um about it. So definitely got
a lot of um issues and challenges still
to to come in the next few meetings.
>> And thank you Despa.
Um and uh next um we have Dr. Larry
Leman. Uh Larry, if you don't mind,
you're next up.
>> Good. Nice to see everybody again. We um
had a meeting this morning at the end of
life committee. Um most of our meetings
have been information gathering, guest
speakers. This is where we started
drilling down on a lot of different um
you know, logistics to actually get
people up and running. So we focused on
things like what would be involved in
getting approval to be doing at your
home, what would be or what do we mean
mean by end of life and doing that. So I
thought it was really a great good
meeting. We're going to meet again on
the 18th of September. You know, our
plan as far as rules and regulations is
to be sort of downstream on several of
the ones that are there now because they
obviously affect how you plan for end of
life. So ours will probably be uh later
in the year.
Good to see everybody.
>> Thank you, Dr. Leman. And uh last but
not least, um Ian uh for you and your
committees.
>> Hi. Yes, I'm the chair of the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee there. We've been working on
general guidance for um prep sessions,
administration sessions, integration
sessions, um and just kind of general
guidance, not really rulem, but best
practices based on the evidence that we
have. And it's been going pretty good.
I've loved the discussions in those
meetings. Um, patient qualification and
safety has kind of analyzed their
initial risk um
like risky co- conditions and uh safety
practices and has also worked to uh
recommend to the board and we'll discuss
after initial rule making um some
additional qualifying conditions. So,
that's a fun thing. And then but in
terms of those two, they've been both
running very smoothly and um
>> and then I was the last one, right?
>> Yes. Ian, you were
>> perfect. All right, so now we can get to
our um actual update of today and it's
to focus on what we need next for rulem.
Um so we've been, you know, asking from
Brenda's committee for a while. Thank
you, Brenda, for all that you have done.
Next up on the list is DESBA committee.
Um we need some
um guidance on how to best execute that
um patient equity fund, what that means,
how that affects, you know, rural
communities and that kind of thing. I've
loved the discussion so far. I'm not
saying you need it by Tuesday. Um but
just you know facilitating those
discussions and continuing that process
forward um is really what I see as the
next priority but I will open it up to
the rest of the board as what you guys
feel.
I would say okay. [laughter]
I mean I think I think that that next on
the list um is it's really important and
it has been um
uh trying to use positive language here.
It has been challenging to kind of
really think about you know how to go
about attacking this. And I know that a
lot of what we're working here is to do
recommendations to kind of, you know,
you think better when you have more
people like involved in the process of
like what about this and what about that
and what about you know so um I really
appreciate everyone's input into
thinking like you know we don't want to
leave um people um you know it's just
how to how to focus but also hold on to
these various different variables that
are necessary. to think about. Um and um
the money problem. I hated word problems
in school. Um so this is like probably
the best case scenario of the of using a
word problem in math [laughter] that
I've ever had to experience. Kids stay
in school and listen to your word
problems. This is the best use of that
um scenario.
>> Definitely. And I mean money issues are
always going to be the most
controversial and your committee deals
most directly with a money issue. Um I
mean all of our committees touch on them
obviously they all incur costs but we
don't have to put a specific number on
those costs. Um and not necessarily that
the committee has to put a specific
number. They may just advise, you know,
general guidance, say, "Hey, we should
do a tearing method or we should
allocate some funds to rural communities
so that they can build healing centers
or alternatives like that." Um, not
necessarily. They need $467.32
to raton and like that's not we don't
need that much detail, but um it is
definitely a complicated subject. So, I
appreciate your eagerness.
I'm I am what is it? Trying to manifest
Ganesha. There are no circumstances that
we can't get through and get around and
push through. So,
>> perfect. All right. and then Chris.
>> Um, so
seems to me that we need to
um kind of work on guidance for how
[snorts] uh I I think our program is
going to work and what specifically
needs to be trained
for facilitators in the New Mexico
program. like, [snorts] you know, how uh
how we're going to handle touch and all
of those things and guidance from our
um
if we're going to do specific guidance
on dosing. I think that's another big
one. Um I've gotten questions from
cultivators around,
[clears throat] you know, if we're
they're going to make capsules, what
size those capsules should be. like are
are we going to put strict dosing
parameters on
uh certain conditions or guidelines? I
would prefer we leave it open to, you
know, discussion between patient and
practitioners, but I'm not sure where
you all are leaning on that type of
stuff. Um, and then also the data
collection side of this and the the the
tracking stuff. I know Dan's committee's
been working really hard on that, but
seems like that all needs to be in place
pretty pretty quickly here if we're
going to we're going to treat people by
December. Um, so just a few thoughts
>> and then Dominic.
>> Yeah, thank you Ian and Chris. Thank you
very much because you actually you and I
were raising our hands about the same
time and you hit on the two points I was
going to raise which is uh the best
practices part and so that's something
that really the dosage administration
committee and the patient qualification
committees have been tackling and what
we are actually doing on the department
side is compiling all of those
recommendations and so I think uh once
the equity piece is done is bringing
those recommendations to the board um to
really look at have that continual
discussion, see what may need uh further
uh discussions or information and sort
of working through those aspects. And
then the next piece on that is exactly
as you said the data piece and um you
know we already have some of that
already in the some of the current
proposals and regulations but there
needs to be a lot more and uh and uh
we're well I think the the REC committee
has been doing a great job in figuring
some of that out and I don't think it's
quite yet ready but probably not in the
too distant future and I see Dan is
nodding his head so I'm going to take
that as Dan's in agreement but I'll let
Dan speak on
Yeah, no problem. On the September 11th
meeting, that was going to be the the
next thing that we're bringing up. So,
we needed to get past the reporting
framework, the quality improvement and
uh harm reduction framework. And so,
those were kind of the things that the
group wanted to say like here are the
reporting periods that we need to make
sure we're collecting data. Here are the
reasons why we're collecting the data.
And so, now we actually go into here's
the data that needs to be collected to
feed back in. and they'll be divided up
into one is core and one is extended
because we know the core is something
that the program is definitely going to
need in order to have viability and
efficacy. The extended would be great
when we're talking about research and
doing uh ongoing like improvements in
the program. So the group is one is
separating those two things out and uh
they've been working to get us to the
September 11th. We're hoping that we can
get that kind of framework at least the
core specifically in place for consensus
at that meeting. So, please be part of
that meeting on September 11th, 9:00 to
11:00 to to hear and to provide comments
back on that.
All righty. Thank you. Um, and
[clears throat] yeah, the data
collection, I've been a part of a few of
those committees. I haven't made it to
all of them, but the work that has been
done there is I am not a data analytical
mind. I look I can barely use Excel. Um,
so just it is astounding to me um the
work that they're doing and just thank
you guys from the bottom of my heart.
Um, but I will allow any other
questions, comments, concerns. We didn't
have a whole lot to go over this
meeting. We just kind of wanted to catch
up with the department um the committees
and just reenter all of our thinking,
see where we are at and where we need to
go. And I think we have a good next goal
which is that um patient equity fund. Um
that doesn't mean everyone else and
every other committee put down
everything and stop. No, please continue
working. Um but for probably what will
be discussed at the next meeting is
either going to be training and
education um if they have their
recommendations completed or um the
patient equity if they do just depending
on which is more divisive or
controversial and that kind of thing.
Um, but yeah, that's kind of what I
have. Does anyone else have any other
questions, comments, concerns,
additions?
I kind of do. Sorry, Brenda. I just
um
I don't want to lie. I know we It's It's
the weekend. Um,
it Yeah, with the equity fund and I know
that quite a few of the people I can see
on the call at least um have
participated in the um in the uh equity
fund and I know we're going to have a
meeting on Tuesday. Um but just for a
couple of them who have not had a chance
to participate. Yeah, I think that this
is a really big challenge um to kind of
really put and integrate all these other
different pieces like Chris has pointed
out, you know, how we're going to do the
dosing and I'm really glad to see how
like it's starting to really come
together. Um I know that there is like
concern with how this is moving you know
but I I am feeling feeling good about um
you know how it's it's slowly kind of
coming together um in the sense that
there's only so like as and as al as
Dominic has pointed out there's only so
much time in the day that we can really
kind of put together and at the same
time it's also on one hand exhaustive.
I'm not going to downplay, you know, the
number of times that in the committee
I've I've reiterated some of the same
things. We have new people coming in.
We're not able to all attend all of the
meetings all of the time. I did have a
chance to um come into the end of life
care uh meeting today. And I just kind
of want to just broadly, you know, state
that some of the things that I feel like
are might be concerns will hopefully
fall away as not being a concern as it's
starting to kind of move forward and
develop because again like the focus is
and I think we finally kind of started
to realize the focus is the medical
psilocybin pathway and that this is not
necessarily for everyone, even those who
want to be able to participate may not
be able to participate at this time. The
people who even are not aware that this
is an option. you know, that education
is really important and as I was um
speaking to some other people, you know,
that the running the risk of and all
this is in my opinion of patronizing and
being paternalistic about how we're
going to go about this, especially when
it comes to um uh communities that that
this may be hard affecting, you know,
that we think might need this the most.
um that a lot of this is just like we're
trying to create the environment both
financially and also the environment for
the people who feel more comfortable
going to the medicine in this particular
pathway. Um, I don't know if I actually
stated this before, but one of the main
reasons that I wanted to be involved in
this is for people like my own family,
you know, for people like, you know, my
mother or my sister or brother or aunts
or uncles who may have um, you know,
have interest or no interest or not even
realize that this is an option for them
and may feel more comfortable because
there still is a stigma out out there
about the use of this medicine and that
this would be a pathway for the people
who are interested in doing this safely
and I want to be able to provide that
system and that support for everyone um
whether or not they're going underground
that's you know and that's anyone's pri
you know prerogative but specifically
that making sure that we are providing
that environment um for for for everyone
who is who is able to participate um but
also So again, like I said, restating
everything again is just through agency,
through their own agency, how can we
create that bridge and that system
without being patronizing, without being
paternalistic, that you need to have
this. Um, and then also realizing that
going back to the principles of the
medicine in and of itself that yeah,
this does take a long time. You have to
sit with someone. You have to as a
person who is who is facilitating has to
let their own ego go. Whether or not we
have a bunch of abbreviations at the end
of our name
that we have to be with that person in
that connection. And it is our
responsibility to be able to be there
with them. and whether or not, you know,
we charge $200, $100 a session, you
know, it's free and someone doesn't have
to pay, whatever it is, that um the
medicine and and and realizing the
medicine will be able to get to the
people that it needs to get to and
trusting in that and that we have the
support of the community and we have the
support of each other and that we will
be able to get and bring this to the
best place that we possibly can.
December 31st, 11:59,
you know, mountain time. Um, so I just
wanted to kind of make sure that, you
know, I I I know that we're doing this.
Um, and it's it's a big push. Um, but I
think that we this we slowly get all
these pieces in place that it'll start
making more of um, sense getting all
those straight edges of the puzzle
together before we start filling in the
picture.
Thank you, Brenda.
>> Thank you, Desba, for that. That can't
be enough said that. I mean, uh really
it uh as far as education training go,
um you know, we're still working on uh a
lot of the details there. And I wanted
to thank Ann uh Mets for um really
championing a lot of what has been
falling through the cracks a little bit,
but uh we're coming to um I think a
consensus here on a lot of things with
education and training.
um we still have to kind of wait for
everyone else to
come in with their information so we can
apply it to these learning modules what
that's going to be. Um and also too to
um uh
you know to make everyone feel better as
far as like like Chris was saying you
know what about uh touch and things like
that. Um uh that's going to be in in uh
the training and education part you know
uh we don't we want to be respectful and
careful about everyone that we are
treating and also too that um I think
that when we're um rolling this out um
education and training are are going to
hold those um core competencies
there and also too we're not going to be
rein reinventing the wheel. I mean,
there's a lot of of information out
there that we can already have and apply
to our program which is run the test uh
on people where they've been working in
in in their states. So um I think that
uh going forward uh uh we uh as far as
education and training there we we have
the um components that we need and that
uh we're just waiting to uh get you know
these programs in for you know gathering
this information. you know, we need, you
know, that the background of all of that
so us clinicians know where to put all
of that information. Also to um uh
keeping um everything ethical and and uh
making sure that everything is HIPPA
compliant uh as far as education and
training goes. I I there's just so much
that goes into education and training.
However, we do already have a lot of
that information there. We just have to
plug in what all the other committees
have into the education and training so
that when we're ready to roll it out, we
could roll it out and also to be
flexible enough to make changes
especially if they these changes need to
be done uh in a timely manner. Um also
you know where will where will we be
training? Can um individual uh teachers
train in facility that uh meets uh the
standards for uh training in education.
You know is it a big enough place? Are
there enough chairs? You know that kind
of thing. So um there's all of that
whole part of it too that um hasn't
really been discussed a whole lot in
training and education. Uh maybe that's
just a little detail, but um I think uh
more and more people want to know um how
to start to um gather their own
information to go ahead and apply uh to
teach. So um there's still a little bit
of work that needs to be uh done there
but um again um having respect for the
patient having respect for the um
medicine is u going to be something that
is going to be taught all along in
education and training.
>> Thank you. and Chris.
So, I guess um
I'm feeling a little uneasy about the
current regulations going through on the
25th. I don't know that we're ready. And
if we keep pushing forward, are we
really going to spend the time we need
to amending
um those regulations?
I think there's a, you know, we're
getting closer on the training aspects
and I know people have been working
really hard on that and I applaud all
that. But, um,
you know, our next committee meeting is
on the 21st and then we're publishing
rules on the 25th.
Um,
I think
you know, there's still a lot of
community push back on the certifying
clinician piece of this. And I'm going
to disagree with you, Brenda, that we
are not recreating the wheel. We are.
We're not following either of the state
access models that are seem to be
working in Oregon and Colorado. We're
recreating the wheel here in New Mexico
and we're doing it on an accelerated
timeline
and uh
I don't think it's going to make for an
accessible program and I think we're
making a lot of mistakes in the process
and I wondering how the other board
members feel about
uh this next
roll out of rules being um published on
the 25th.
Thank you, Chris. Um, I'll open the
discussion up for that. Personally, I
have no disagreement with
those aspects. I understand the
community push back, but at the same
time, um, it's the law. We have to
follow the law. Um, I don't want to live
in a country where the executive branch
can make whatever laws they want. Um,
so I
can't support that we would be able to
amend SB219 on our own. It requires that
we make sure someone is medically
appropriate for psilocybin care
and that's what we have to do. Uh
alongside that the secretary has told us
you know or not the secretary the
department has told us they will not pro
promulgate a rule without a medical
certification and ultimately in the law
the rulem authority lies with the
department of health. So I don't know
that that aspect has anything to do with
the 25th date. Um, but I do believe
there's plenty of time still for the
training and education committee to
continue to have debates and continue to
work out the problems within the program
before the 25th.
Chris.
Okay.
Um, so the Department of Health is part
of the executive branch, I believe. So
they're the ones making the rules and
you're saying that, you know, they
shouldn't just be able to make whatever
rules they want. Like we're supposed to
do the
>> violate the law.
>> Excuse me. What's that?
>> I'm saying they should not violate the
law. I'm saying the legislature passed a
law
>> and the executive branch enforces that
>> and statute requires that
diagnosis is the entry point to this
program
>> and also that they also that they
coordinate with an advisory board that's
appointed to help set up this program.
>> Yes. But it also requires medical
appropriateness
and
Is there any other professional who can
determine medical appropriateness
outside of those who can also prescribe
medicine? There are definitely people
that can do behavioral health
appropriateness.
But I understand where the department is
coming from. They have to follow the
law.
Thank you. already. Um, any other
questions, comments, concerns, or
additions?
Ryan?
>> Yeah, I I will just say um
in my current role, I oversee the policy
department for Medicaid or the policy
bureau.
Uh I do think it's an iterative process.
we kind of constantly are in the process
of uh improving laws or improving rules
based off new laws passed by the
legislature based off of public feedback
and comment. So the idea that we set the
NMAC the rules once and and then it's
done. I would say that legislation is an
iterative process. We can look at some
of the other kind of key landmark sort
of things we've set up in the state. um
you know, most recently like
a sidebar, but um some of our death with
dignity acts had to be amended multiple
years in a row until we got to a point
that worked for both the providers and
the patients. So, um I hear your
apprehension. Um I hear the public's
apprehension. Um and I would say it's a
process and it's an iterative process.
So, it's good to participate. It's good
to be vocal about what you believe and
uh but also I hope that you can trust
the process that we'll get to the right
spot um as as time moves on.
>> Thank you. And Desba.
>> Um thank you Ryan.
>> Kenan Ryan. Oh
>> Kenan. Ryan's my last name. Don't worry
about it. It's I have two first names
that just kind of exist as a two first
names.
>> Agent K.
>> Agent K. Okay. Um, thank you for kind of
saying that. I think what what it sounds
like, and I know that this I don't want
to necessarily speak for Chris, but what
it sounds like is just, you know, we're
trying to kind of understand the
difference between like interpretation
of something and how do we
in our best practices? Well, all this
language is just making so much more
confusion. But how do we best into the
best of our ability interpret how these
things are being then um carried out? Um
what does it say specifically? I'm not a
lawyer. I just will say that I love the
difference between may and shall. The
first time I learned that blew my mind
that just a singular word change in
something can mean a huge significance.
Um, and I think that might be somewhere
the communication is kind of or the
understanding of like how this is all
being you know processed. So I
appreciate that. Um
uh you know we're understanding like
what it sounds like also too from what
uh Kenan is saying is that there is a
place that we have to start and I also
hear that from Dominic. there's a place
that we have to start and you know it
can be either going up or down but the
barometer is for that is kind of feeling
based on past experience having worked
with the um cannabis or any others um
that we might not necessarily be privy
to because this is first time board
member on the facil advisory board um
that you know what that barometer might
be and that it can actually move
according to these things but if we
start too low then that might be a
disservice. If we start too high that
again might be a disservice. But if we
start somewhere in the middle it's
seeming like then we can have the
ability to move based on what the needs
of the real community is. But that is
not an experience that I own is not an
experience that I have have have had nor
is it a skill set that I know you know
where this is might lead to. But I feel
like you know understanding specifically
the roles of the department of health
that we are not a part of the department
of health. We are the advisory board
recommending something to a body of
people who have experience in this and
have done these things in the past. It
doesn't mean again that it's going to be
set in stone, but it is a place that we
are going to start and we are advising
with the best of our ability um in all
of our experience that yes, we do need
to be very vocal about hey, we need to
be listening more and it's like you know
essentially lawyers saying yes, it has
been noted that you know this has been
strongly objected um and that we can
move on forward with this but and maybe
we can return to it and we can revisit.
I mean, you know, I'm not there's how
many other people that are here on this
meeting? That's not representative of
the other two million people that are in
the state. I mean, it is and it's not to
be very very honest. So, how are we, you
know, we're doing the best that we can
and we all are doing the best that we
can and I don't want to take uh, you
know, that for granted. Um, but I just
feel like there is definitely some
miscommunication about or an and
understanding of exactly where we're
trying to move this so that we can
actually get through this and not that
we are essentially stuck on this ship.
Um, unlike our uh navy um but that we
can actually move somewhere and and and
and move forward with our decisions.
Thank you. And Larry,
>> yeah, I um [clears throat]
you know, I've had a lot of concerns
over the last month, which you know,
I've expressed here in other committees
regarding the training, the didactic,
and the practicum. I I would agree with
what Brenda says. You know, we've Brenda
and I with other committee members there
have I think made a lot of progress.
We've shared that and met with the DO.
So, I'm really hopeful that over the
next week or 10 days that um with those
meetings that that will actually come
out and it'll be something that that we
have a consensus and are happy about.
So, that's that's my hope on uh hope on
that.
>> Thank you. Um yeah, and for
clarification, I if I were omnipotent,
it would be sold at like dispensaries.
However,
>> I recognize that they passed a medical
psilocybin bill and part of that is
intersecting with the medical system and
there are its faults, there are its good
parts, but it is that intersection
between our medical system and
psilocybin that we are trying to walk
this very nice line and trying to
implement. I don't think anyone on the
board side nor the department side is
intentionally trying to ignore or
dismiss any concern. I think what's
happening is it's sometimes you when
you're in a group you um form and then
storm and then you eventually start
moving forward and you start making your
actual group decisions. And I think
sometimes we have to disagree. Sometimes
something we don't like gets moved
forward and that's okay. Um I haven't
been 100% right in any of my committees
and proposing you know a draft and
saying this was perfect. I didn't have
to make any changes. That doesn't
happen. I have to go through and you
know modify and continue moving forward
so that we can find that compromise in
the best way that's possible. Um, I
really liked how Desba used the term
this is a pathway, but it's not the only
pathway and there's nothing stopping a,
you know, construction company from
building a new pathway. Um, outside of
this medical system, kind of like how
they did for cannabis. Um, but we have
to recognize where we're at now, the
path we are on now, and work the best we
can to help shape it in the best way we
can for the patients that are going to
be served.
Brenda.
>> Yeah. I just want to um emphasize that
every therapist, nurse, doctor
um and um other other people that will
be doing this work. We have to go
through a lot of training for ethics. If
we follow the rule of ethics and um
patients privacy and uh the data that
we'll be collecting and uh the training
that we're going to be doing, ethics is
like the number one thing that we all
are held to and that if there's anyone
that is
not going to follow that, then they
shouldn't even be in this program and
shouldn't even be in the profession that
they're in. This is why we we go through
all of the schooling and and training
and working with our clients.
um even as a therapist seeing people one
on- one uh we also have uh guidelines
there for us if we're seeing people in
person or on tele health. So there's
these ethic ethics are held to a very
high standard for people in the medical
profession and if we follow that and
try to instill that people are safe and
uh abiding by the these rules and
regulations
that is what we should always follow and
also people's personal
integrity and relationship and standards
and values that each and every one of us
come into the this profession to um to
do. We are also bringing that into the
medical psilocybin program and this is
just another added layer of standards
that we are going to be following.
Thank you. Um, yeah, and it reminds me
of,
and this is not a reason, I don't know,
the department has their reasons. I
don't work on it. Um but
>> one of the things that we
do get by having a physician there is in
the court of public opinion
if a federal prosecutor decided to try
to charge a patient.
They would have a lot harder time in the
court of public opinion if it was a
doctor and a patient and they were
taking their medication.
While the program is new, it could make
sense to be a little more strict. Now,
>> given that the other states have not
done that and we haven't seen really any
consequences, um I wouldn't apply that
as a reason, but do look at all of the
consequences of removing healthcare and
what that does for
the
perception of the program as well.
But does anyone else have anything else
that they would like to add?
All righty. Well, since Brenda, we are
going to be discussing your uh
committee's work at the next meeting,
what would when works best for you? When
would you like us to meet again?
>> Okay. Uh so we'll be meeting on the
21st. Uh I I'm doing the morning which
is 9 and 11. Uh September. Um
uh what do we have open in September on
Friday?
>> Was that to us Brenda to the department?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Uh, so in um September, it looks
like currently September 4th is open,
although I usually would not recommend
that simply because that is the Friday
before a 3-day weekend and many people
take that time. So, I wouldn't recommend
that. Um, September 11th currently has
the research and continuous
uh improvement meeting in the morning,
but the afternoon is free. Um, and then
similar on the 18th, the Oh, I'm sorry.
Actually, the 18th is at this point is
booked. Um, and uh
let us see. Yeah. So, it looks and then
the 25th of September um the meeting
could occur, but just to let everybody
know, I will not be available on that
date. Um but that is otherwise open both
in the morning and the afternoon. So
right now it is looking like the best
times would the best time would actually
be on the 11th in the afternoon.
>> Okay.
>> And then Larry, you had a comment.
>> Do that. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um so one of the reasons why I
think the regs were were postponed is
because there had been a commitment to
the um training committee to be able to
work on them. The training committee and
myself and other people spent a lot of
energy working on those. Um, I just want
to make sure there's a pathway from the
meeting that Brenda is committee next
week for that to be incorporated into
the ranks. I think that's really
important. Otherwise, we're kind of back
where we were. So, um, it doesn't mean
that we have to meet before that. I'm
not sure maybe it's a potential Brenda
and I have a meeting with Dom, you know,
that's happening next week, but I just
want to, you know, just make sure that
there's a way that that information and
those potential changes can be
incorporated. Yes. And and actually to
answer that, Larry, as we've actually
said many times, when the rules are
published, they are not set in stone.
It's still open to those that advisement
to those changes. Um and so that does
happen where we do make alterations
based upon other comments andor
submissions from uh the committee and
other people as well. So yes, that is a
possibility and and is a part of that
process.
I just want to make sure I'm clear
because it's been So Brenda and I are
meeting with you next week presenting
some of that information. Can that
potentially be put into the rules and
rags before they're posted on August
25th?
>> Yes. If that is something that the
department agrees on that that's the
best path forward. Yes.
>> Perfect. But I just want to make sure
that
>> it too. It's like thank you.
>> We've been working really hard on this
D.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I agree.
Absolutely. That's important. Okay.
>> So, we're we're we're I was really
thinking that, you know, the you know,
after all of that, moving in into
September
um if there was any availability to to
um have a meeting then. And you're
saying, Dominic, what the September 11th
in the afternoon?
>> Yes, that's correct.
>> Fourth.
>> Okay. The 11th. Well, the the fourth is
open as well. I just would recommend not
the fourth only because it's the Friday
before the three-day weekend, but that
if this committee does so, that's fine
with the department. I just think about
all the other people who take time and
would want to participate from the
public who may not because, you know,
they may not have a lot of other time
and so they're they're, you know,
utilizing that three-day weekend to get
a little extra time without taking other
time off. So, but if this if this board
decides for the board, the department is
able to handle that.
>> I would let the department decide. Um,
if you want to have two meetings on one
day, you can do that. Or if you want to
have one on the Friday,
>> it's it's a lot to have two meetings
[laughter]
on the Friday. It's it so um uh so
just to have I guess the for the
training and education part you know
we're going to be doing that you know
this month uh but I'm I'm really
thinking about you know having just the
meeting to discuss what we've been doing
in the month of August for training and
education. Um
uh so the the the 25th is not is is not
good or but we're okay. We could do the
25th. Um
>> yeah, you mean September 25th, Brenda?
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> You can just I will not be able to be in
attendance.
>> You will not be here.
>> Okay. Um well, if we get a lot of work
done, which I'm hoping, uh you know,
next week, um
uh would it be possible to do an
afternoon meeting on on either the 11th
or the 18th?
>> And then Larry also has a comment.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
Uh, [clears throat] and just to say that
the 18th is is booked at this point, but
the 11th in the afternoon would work.
>> Okay. Uh, Larry, does that sound good to
you?
>> Oh, yeah. No, I'm I'm fine. I was just
going to mention that I thought the 18th
was filled up. I'm fine with the 11th or
the 25th.
>> Okay. All right.
>> All right. So, the 11th at one.
>> Okay, that sounds fine. Yes. Perfect.
>> Cool.
All righty. Well, then I thank everyone
for coming. We will go ahead and turn
over to public comment.
>> Okay. And just as a reminder for those
who would like to provide public
comment, you just need to raise your
hand. Um public comment is limited to
three minutes uh per individual. Um but
uh we have that on open and if you'd
like to raise your hand, we'll call on
you once we enable your mic and then you
just need to unmute it on your side and
um Jorge has just put that those
instructions into the chat and uh so go
ahead and raise your hand if you're
interested in providing additional
comment.
All right, Denali, I have enabled your
mic.
>> Good afternoon, everybody. Um,
yeah, I I don't have the most organized
thoughts. I'm just reflecting on
>> [clears throat]
>> um some conversation in today's meeting
around the parameters of the statute and
whether the requirement for medical
appropriateness requires
the design that the department um seems
to be moving forward with around
certifying clinician. Um, and I I just
want to iterate medical appropriateness
and medical screening and medical safety
are an incredibly important part of the
viability of this program of patient and
community safety and community trust in
in what we're doing. Um and and the
concerns that that I and others I think
have shared um is that those goals of
safety may not be achieved by the
certifying clinician
um lensure design. Uh I I think it would
be really appropriate for the department
to regulate minimum requirements for an
advanced medical screening based perhaps
on some of the contraindication
uh information that's being developed in
in one of Ian's committees. Um things
like uncontrolled hypertension, history
of psychosis, like where do we want to
require a heightened medical screening?
But the access issue um is is really
acute if we require it for everyone. You
know, folks who are working already with
lenture
uh as um in our behavioral health uh
[clears throat]
continuum are already, you know,
honoring the boundaries of their scope
of practice and um and making referrals
when things are beyond their scope of
practice. And and I think I I'd like to
see us, you know, relying more heavily
on on that than uh requiring um this one
single entry point.
>> Thank you, Denali.
Greg, I have enabled your microphone.
>> Um, I think the conversation around what
is medical in the context of this
program
as we've
unfolded the process,
it uh continues to like reveal itself.
And I think codifying language when we
put the rules for training and education
together is super important and we have
an opportunity to finetune some very
important words. Um leveraging off the
depth of what Desba mentioned earlier,
shall versus may. Um words make a huge
difference. And I think
when we're looking at the medical
appropriateness, it's a mental health
diagnosis and that can be performed by a
licensed provider
and licensed providers can be several
types of things. Facilitators or
facilitators and then what we currently
are calling the certifying clinician. I
think that we should put it into the
correct context of medical screener or
medical screening. So the medical
condition is the psychological
condition and the container of care is a
therapeutic structure and the medical
screening is for physical safety.
That is my comment and recommendation.
>> Thank you, Greg.
>> And no more hands are have been raised,
Eden. So, we'll turn it back over to
you.
>> All righty. Well, thank you everyone
from for showing up today. uh especially
from the department and all of the
community members who have spoken. Um I
really appreciate you taking the time to
be here and making the program as good
for patients as we can. We may not
always agree on everything, but as the
fact that you showed up here today to
help out and to still voice your opinion
is incredibly important to the
development of this program. So, thank
you all once again and have a great rest
of your weekend.
And on behalf of the department, thank
you everybody for your participation in
your work and have a great Friday and
weekend.